My name's Conan Edogawa.
Меня зовут Конан Эдогава.
High school student Shinichi was forced to take a drug that shrunk him.
Я школьник Синъити, которого уменьшили ядом.
Although smaller, my intelligence remains the same!
Но разум остался прежним!
I solve cases not even adults can!
Я решаю дела, неподвластные взрослым!
Sorry for the wait! Today's Conan is a one-hour special!
А вот и долгожданный часовой спецвыпуск «Конана»!
The Piano Sonata "Moonlight" Murders.
«Убийства под фортепианную "Лунную" сонату»!
The first end of the century in 100 years
Сотня лет прошла, и век подошёл к концу...
When told to cry, I laughed instead
Скажет кто-то слёзы лить? Рассмеюсь в ответ!
The first end of the century in a long, long time
Много лет прошло, и век подошёл к концу...
We're leaping into a wide open world
Безграничный мир нас ждёт — так бежим скорей!
The things I tried to understand as a child
С детства в толк не мог я взять, вещей различных я не понимал...
remain a mystery even as an adult
И даже в жизни взрослой... загадкою остались!
I'm neither a hotshot nor especially great
Я, может, и не герой, не так хорош я собой,
All I understand is the pounding of my heart
и понимаю я лишь, как сердце быстро бьётся!
It's neither an answer nor the truth
Ответ ещё не нашёл и истину не обрёл...
All I have faith in is the pounding of my heart
Верю я лишь в то, что сердце быстро бьётся.
That and nothing else
Лишь в то, что сердце бьётся.
The Piano Sonata "Moonlight" Murders.
«Убийства под фортепианную "Лунную" сонату»!
Why does the famous detective Kogoro Mori have to go to a stupid island
И почему известный детектив Когоро Мори
when he could be spending his time at a flower viewing party?!
должен ехать на чёртов остров, когда мог бы любоваться цветением?
It's all because of that letter I got a week ago!
И всё из-за письма, которое пришло неделю назад!
On the night of the next full moon,
«В ночь будущего полнолуния
shadows will once again begin to disappear from Tsukikage Island.
с острова Цукикагэ вновь начнут исчезать тени.
Investigate. Keiji Aso.
Расследуйте. Кэйдзи Асо».
Mori Detective Agency.
Детективное агентство Мори слушает.
Two days until the next full moon.
До полнолуния осталось два дня.
I've transferred half a million to your bank account.
Я перевёл полмиллиона на ваш счёт.
You had best come.
Буду ждать.
Hold on! Who the heck are you?!
П-погодите! Кто вы такой?!
Keiji Aso from Tsukikage Island.
Кэйдзи Асо с острова Цукикагэ.
Hey, wait! Hello?!
Минутку! Алло, алло?
He didn't even bother for me to accept him as a client or not!
Он даже не дождался подтверждения!
What's to complain about?
Чего возмущаешься?
At least we get to relax on a small island near Izu!
Зато отдохнём на островке у Идзу!
Right, Conan-kun?
Согласен, Конан?
Tsukikage Island
Остров Цукикагэ
Keiji Aso...
Кэйдзи Асо...
I don't see anyone by that name in here...
Здесь такого имени нет...
Look harder, could you?!
Поищите ещё, да как следует!
I have a letter from him right here, after all...
У меня письмо от него...
But he's not in the list of residents,
Но он не заселялся,
and I just moved to this island, so I don't know that much about--
а я сам только приехал, так что мало знаю...
Is something the matter?
Что-то не так?
Chief, it seems that these people have been hired by a resident here...
Шеф, похоже, их нанял кто-то из жителей...
Hired?
Нанял?
That's right. By someone named Keiji Aso...
Да. Кто-то по имени Кэйдзи Асо...
What? Did you say Keiji Aso?!
Что? Кэйдзи Асо, говорите?!
That's not possible! He's been dead for over 10 years!
Не может этого быть! Он  мёртв уже более десяти лет!
He was a famous pianist who was born and raised on this island.
Он был известным пианистом, родился и вырос на этом острове.
It was the night of a full moon, 12 years ago...
Двенадцать лет назад в полнолуние...
It was his first time home in a long time,
Он спустя долгое время вернулся
so he held a concert in the town's community center.
и устроил концерт в дворце культуры.
But afterwards, he suddenly shut his family and himself inside their home
Но затем он вдруг закрылся дома с семьёй
and lit the place on fire!
и поджёг его!
He allegedly stabbed his wife and daughter to death
Говорят, он заколол жену и дочь, а затем
and then continued to play the piano as the fire raged on,
продолжал играть на рояле как заведённый,
almost as if he was possessed by something.
пока вокруг полыхало пламя.
Beethoven's piano sonata... "Moonlight."
Фортепианную сонату Бетховена... также известную как «Лунная».
A letter from a dead man...
Письмо от мертвеца...
What a nasty prank.
Какое издевательство.
That's not necessarily the case.
Возможно, дело в другом.
Your fee was paid, plus the letter was postmarked from this island.
За работу ведь заплатили, да и марки на письме с этого острова.
I bet someone on the island wants you to look into Keiji Aso's affairs!
Кто-то наверняка хочет, чтобы вы расследовали дело Кэйдзи Асо.
He's right!
Точно!
The mayor here used to be a good friend of his,
Мэр раньше дружил с Кэйдзи,
maybe he can tell us something!
возможно, он чем-то поможет.
Yeah...
И то верно...
They said the mayor's over at the community center, right?
Кажется, он был в дворце культуры?
Now then, Kenta-kun. Make sure to keep warm when you sleep.
Слушай, Кэнта. Укутайся потеплее, когда будешь спать.
Okay, I will! Bye!
Хорошо! Пока-пока!
Bye!
Пока!
Excuse me!
Извините!
Where is the community center?
А где дворец культуры?
You turn that corner and then keep going straight.
Заверните за угол, а затем идите прямо.
Wait, are you folks from Tokyo?!
Неужели вы из Токио?
That's right. We got off the ship just now.
Да. Только что приплыли.
I live in Tokyo too!
Я тоже родом из Токио!
But this island is so much nicer, wouldn't you agree?
Но этот остров куда лучше, не находите?
The air's fresh, and it's nice and quiet!
Воздух свежий, жизнь тихая и мирная!
Protect the island's fishing industry! Vote for Masato Shimizu!
Встаньте на стражу рыбного промысла! Голосуйте за Масато Симидзу!
Well, maybe not too quiet.
Ну, не совсем тихая.
The mayoral election is coming up, you see.
Скоро будут выборы мэра.
The mayoral election, huh?
Выборы мэра, да?
The candidates are Shimizu-san, who represents the fishermen,
Кандидатами стали представитель рыбаков Симидзу,
current mayor Kuroiwa-san, whose popularity is dwindling as of late,
действующий мэр Куроива, растерявший былую популярность,
and Kawashima-san, the wealthiest man on the island.
а также Кавасима, самый богатый на острове.
My patients have been telling me that Kawashima-san will probably--
Говорят, что Кавасима, скорее всего...
That's alright, Nurse. We're not really that interested in the election...
Всё в порядке, медсестра. Мы не особо заинтересованы...
That's Doctor Narumi Asai.
Врач Наруми Асай (26)
I have an actual license, you know!
У меня есть лицензия!
Oh, you're a doctor...
Так вы врач...
If you folks are headed to the community center,
Если вы идёте во дворец культуры,
you can meet the three of them there!
то встретитесь с кандидатами!
Tonight they're holding a 3rd-year memorial for Kameyama-san,
Сегодня третья годовщина со смерти Камэямы,
our previous mayor.
прошлого мэра.
Your previous mayor?
Прошлого мэра?
A 3rd-year memorial?
Третья годовщина?
Don't let the mayor continue his reign of terror!
Не допустим тирании со стороны мэра!
Give me a break.
Во дают.
How dare they do this on the night of the previous mayor's memorial?!
Действующий мэр острова Цукикагэ Тацудзи Куроива (56)
They're really getting on my nerves!
Как же они надоели.
Hirata! What're you doing?! Shut them up already!
Хирата, чем ты там занят? А ну угомони их!
Yes, ma'am!
Да, госпожа.
Don't let the mayor continue his reign of terror!
Не допустим тирании со стороны мэра!
Hey, everything okay?
Всё в порядке?
Is what okay, Shuichi?
О чём ты, Сюити?
They're saying this election ain't looking so good for your old man.
Говорят, у твоего старика всё не так радужно.
Indeed. It would seem the citizens favor me the most.
Вот именно. Похоже, я больше всех приглянулся жителям.
That's only because you know how to use money.
Ты просто умело управляешься с деньгами.
Which I learned from you, of course.
У вас научился.
There's a man here who wants to see the mayor!
К мэру пришли посетители!
Who is it, at a time like this?!
Да кому я понадобился?!
A detective from Tokyo...
Детективу из Токио...
What? A detective?!
Что? Детективу?!
Come on, how long are they going to make me wait?!
И долго нам ещё ждать его?
Huh? Where's Conan-kun?
Что? А где Конан?
A piano...
Рояль...
Stop that, Conan-kun!
Ну куда ты, Конан!
Huh? What a huge room!
О, какая огромная комната.
So the rear of the community center is on the water's edge...
Так дворец культуры находится у воды...
This piano sure is dirty...
Какой грязный инструмент...
You'd think they could at least clean it once in a while...
Вот бы его хоть иногда чистили...
No, don't touch that!
Не трогайте его!
That's the cursed piano that Aso-san played the day he died!
Это проклятый рояль, на котором Асо играл перед смертью!
Cursed? Give me a break...
Проклятый? Да ладно вам...
Aso-san wasn't the only one!
И не только Асо!
The same thing happened to the last mayor!
То же случилось с прошлым мэром!
You mean Isamu Kameyama-san,
Вы об Исаму Камэяме,
the person they're holding the memorial for today?
у которого сегодня годовщина смерти?
Yes. It happened 2 years ago.
Да. Это случилось два года назад...
It was the night of a full moon.
В ночь полнолуния.
I was passing by the community center, which should have been empty,
Я проходил мимо, казалось бы, пустого дворца культуры,
when I heard the sounds of a piano coming from inside.
как вдруг услышал оттуда звуки рояля.
When I called out to see who was there, the music stopped.
Когда я спросил, есть ли там кто, музыка прекратилась.
Inside, I found Kameyama-san!
И внутри был Камэяма!
He had died of a heart attack.
Он умер от сердечного приступа.
And the music he had been playing before he died
А перед смертью он играл то же произведение,
was the same piece Aso-san had performed in the fire: "Moonlight."
что исполнял Асо при пожаре... «Лунную» сонату.
After that, this piano came to be known as the Cursed Piano.
С тех пор этот рояль считается проклятым.
Conan-kun!
Конан!
Seems normal enough to me.
По-моему, вполне нормальный.
Anyway, please wait by the front door until the memorial is over!
Подождите у входа до конца поминок!
Oh, you're still here?
О, вы ещё здесь?
Narumi-san! Are you going to the memorial?
Наруми! Вы тоже пришли?
Yes. Kameyama-san was the first person I autopsied when I came here.
Да. Когда приехала сюда, я делала аутопсию Камэяме.
I thought I would burn some incense in his honor.
Хотелось почтить его память.
Oh, this is Shimizu-san. I happened to meet him on the way.
А, это Симидзу. Мы встретились по пути.
Hello, my name's Shimizu. lt's nice to meet you!
Меня зовут Симидзу, рад знакомству!
Hey, Kawashima.
Эй, Кавасима.
You hired a detective to dig up some dirt on me, didn't you?!
Ты нанял детектива, чтобы он под меня копал?
Don't be stupid.
Чушь.
Running away?!
Сбегаешь?!
Bathroom.
Иду в туалет.
It's strange.
Странно.
That piano should have remained unused for years now,
На рояле не играли годами,
but it produced a perfect sound.
но у него нет проблем со звуком.
Someone must be tuning it secretly.
Возможно, кто-то втайне его настраивал.
For some purpose...
По неизвестной причине...
And what exactly was that letter trying to say?
Да и что значило это письмо?
This song!
Неужели это...
...Moonlight! Oh no!
«Лунная» соната! Чёрт!
Conan-kun!
Конан!
Hey! Little boy!
Эй, мальчик.
It's Kawashima-san!
Это Кавасима!
Too late!
Опоздали.
He's dead.
Он мёртв.
What?!
Что?!
Ran. Contact the local police station!
Ран. Свяжись с местной полицией.
Right!
Да.
Dr. Narumi. Please inspect the body.
Наруми. Обследуйте тело.
Now I see!
Вот оно что!
That letter warned that another person on Tsukikage Island
Письмо — предупреждение, что ещё один
would die on the night of a full moon!
человек умрёт на острове в полнолуние!
It's the curse! It's the curse of the piano!
Это проклятие! Проклятие рояля!
There's no curse. It's this tape recorder that's playing the music.
Нет никакого проклятия. Звук исходит из магнитофона.
This was a murder designed to resemble the previous two incidents!
Это подстроенное и внешне похожее убийство!
Murder?!
Убийство?!
Hey now, don't be getting ahead of yourself.
Эй, не надо придумывать.
Who the hell are you, anyway?!
Кто вы вообще такой?!
I'm a famous detective from Tokyo-- Kogoro Mori!
Я известный детектив из Токио, Когоро Мори.
Oh, the astronaut?
А, тот астронавт?
No, he's the one in all those mystery novels.
Нет, который в детективных романах.
That's Akechi.
Там же Акэти.
Then who's this?
А это тогда кто?
Seawater.
Морская вода.
Approximate time of death was 30 minutes to an hour ago.
Примерное время смерти — полчаса-час назад.
He probably died of suffocation.
Скорее всего, умер от удушья.
My guess is that Kawashima-san drowned.
Предполагаю, что Кавасима утонул.
Drowned by someone?
Его кто-то утопил?
I can't say any more without performing an autopsy.
Без аутопсии нельзя сказать наверняка.
I think Dr. Narumi is right.
Думаю, что Наруми права.
See, there's a suit jacket on the beach outside.
На пляже виднеется пиджак.
I bet it belongs to Kawashima-san.
Думаю, он принадлежит Кавасиме.
There's a trail of water here that goes from the door to the piano
От двери к роялю идёт мокрый след...
and there's mud and sand on Kawashima-san's back.
а на спине Кавасимы видны песок и грязь.
And judging from the fact that the door and windows were all locked,
Судя по тому, что все двери и окна заперты,
and that the first few minutes of the cassette tape are blank...
а первые несколько минут на кассете пустые...
When did he become so...?
И когда он стал таким...
The killer probably took Kawashima-san to the ocean during the memorial,
Скорее всего, убийца отвёл Кавасиму к морю во время поминок,
drowned him,
утопил его,
dragged the body into this room,
затащил тело в комнату,
locked the door,
запер дверь,
turned the tape recorder on, and then exited into the hallway.
включил магнитофон и вышел в коридор.
Right?
Так ведь?
Y-Yeah, sounds about right to me!
Д-да, вполне логично.
Assuming the door to this room was locked,
Учитывая, что дверь была заперта,
there's a high possibility the killer returned to the memorial afterwards,
скорее всего, убийца вернулся на поминки,
since we were at the front door the whole time!
потому как мы сидели у входа.
Are you saying the killer's still among us?!
Намекаете, что убийца в этой комнате?!
Yes, the killer is in this very room.
Верно. Убийца среди нас.
Did anyone here see Kawashima-san leave his seat?
Кто-нибудь видел, как Кавасима ушёл?
I saw him. He said he was going to the restroom.
Да, я видел. Он сказал, что пойдёт в туалет.
Did anybody see anyone else leave their seat?
Кто-нибудь видел, куда именно он пошёл?
As if we could remember every little thing that happened.
Мы не можем запоминать все мелочи.
In that case, did anyone have any grudges with Kawashima-san?
А у кого-нибудь из вас были обиды на Кавасиму?
It's not exactly a grudge,
Не совсем обида,
but the person most happy about his death would be Shimizu-kun,
но больше всего его смерть была на руку Симидзу,
his opponent in the mayoral election!
противнику на выборах.
What?! The same goes for you, Mayor Kuroiwa!
Что? Это и вас касается, мэр Куроива!
Yes, without Kawashima-san,
Ну да, без Кавасимы
As long as a certain someone
Если кое-кто не начнёт
wasn't plotting to steal Kawashima-san's votes, of course.
манипулировать голосами Кавасимы.
What?!
Что?!
Now, now, there!
Госпожа!
Calm down now...
Успокойтесь...
But why did the killer put the body in this room?
Зачем убийца поместил труп именно сюда?
Because the killer wanted to place the blame on the cursed piano.
Просто убийца хотел свалить вину на проклятый инструмент.
Say, just how long has this piano been here?
И долго здесь стоит этот рояль?
It's been here ever since Aso-san donated it 15 years ago.
С тех пор, как пятнадцать лет назад Асо пожертвовал его дворцу.
Aso-san, eh?
Асо, да?
Yes. His name is even on the keyboard lid.
Да. Его имя даже есть под крышкой.
What's this?
Что это?..
It's sheet music.
Это же ноты.
That's strange. This wasn't here when we checked this afternoon.
Странно. Ещё вечером их здесь не было.
Who was that?
Кто бы это мог быть?
Nishimoto-san.
Нисимото.
He did rather well for himself back in the day.
Раньше он ни в чём себе не отказывал.
I hear he spent lots of money on alcohol, women, and gambling...
Тратил деньги на азартные игры, женщин и выпивку...
But after the mayor died 2 years ago,
Но после смерти мэра два года назад
he stopped going out, almost as if he were afraid of something.
он перестал гулять, будто боялся чего-то.
I see.
А.
Wasn't he a childhood friend of yours, Mayor?
Кажется, вы в детстве с ним дружили?
Yes, I suppose you could say that...
Да, можно и так сказать...
Here's a policeman!
Вот полицейский.
You're late, Ran!
Долго же ты, Ран.
But I had to look for him, he wasn't at the police station!
Мне пришлось его искать, в участке его не было!
Who called for me now?
И кто меня вызвал?
This gentleman here. His name is Kogoro Mori.
Вот этот мужчина, Когоро Мори.
Oh, the famous--
О, известный...
That's right!
Да!
Astronaut!
Астронавт!
At any rate, it's getting late.
В любом случае уже поздно.
We can put off collecting information until tomorrow morning.
Расследование можно продолжить завтра.
This was no murder. It was Aso-san's curse.
Какое убийство? Это проклятие Асо.
How horrifying...
Аж страх наводит...
They should just burn that creepy old piano!
Им стоило сжечь этот чёртов старый рояль.
Yeah. Maybe we'd be better off without that thing.
Ну да. Без него, возможно, было бы лучше.
Shuichi?
Сюити?
Your deductions sure surprised me, Conan-kun!
Конан, ты меня удивил своей дедукцией!
He loves playing detective!
Он любит играть в детектива.
Everyone was talking about how amazing his persuasiveness was!
Все удивились, как убедительно звучали его доводы!
I was just pretending to be like Detective Kogoro!
Я просто подражал детективу Когоро!
I always get to see him at work!
Я ведь наблюдаю за его работой.
He's just a baby chick compared to me, though!
По сравнению со мной он совсем ещё птенец.
Well, we'll head back to the hotel now.
А нам пора возвращаться в гостиницу.
I'll see you later then. Please solve this case as quickly as possible.
Ещё увидимся. Раскройте это дело поскорее.
I'd rather not have to examine any more bodies.
Хотелось бы избежать других трупов.
Don't you worry! This'll be a piece of cake with me at the helm!
Не волнуйтесь! Для меня это раз плюнуть!
Whatever. Not even I really know what's going on yet...
Ну даёт. Даже я ещё не успел разобраться...
Wait a second!
Минутку!..
That letter said, "begin to disappear"...
В письме было написано «начнут исчезать»...
Meaning this isn't over yet!
Значит, ничего ещё не кончено!
What? This murder spree has yet to continue?
Что? Серийные убийства продолжатся?
This letter gives warning about that?
И письмо об этом предупреждает?
"Shadows disappearing" means "being enveloped by light."
Исчезновение теней означает поглощение света.
Light stands for the song played at all the murder scenes--Moonlight!
А свет — это произведение на месте преступлений... «Лунная» соната!
Now I see!
Вот оно что.
The song Mr. Aso played in the fire 12 years ago...
Произведение, которое Асо играл двенадцать лет назад...
And the song the mayor played before he died 2 years ago...
Его же играл мэр перед смертью спустя десять лет...
It was Beethoven's piano sonata, Moonlight.
«Лунная» соната Бетховена.
And all three incidents have taken place beside the piano.
Все три инцидента произошли у фортепиано.
You two go back to the hotel!
Возвращайтесь в гостиницу!
Wait!
Погоди!
Ran! Let's go to the community center too!
Ран. Давай тоже пойдём во дворец культуры.
You're crazy if you ask me.
Это явно безумие.
Spending a night with a corpse like this...
Провести ночь с трупом...
And with a kid, too!
ещё и с ребёнком!
I thought I told you to go back!
Говорил же вам возвращаться.
But Conan-kun...
Но Конан...
Tell me, who moved the body without permission?
И кто убрал труп без разрешения?
Me.
Я.
I felt bad for the poor guy, being stuck in that position...
Жалко мне его, остался в такой позе...
You really shouldn't have,
Не стоило так делать,
we're not through investigating the crime scene yet...
мы ещё не закончили обследовать...
Huh? The sheet music's gone.
А? Ноты пропали.
What?!
Что?!
Oh, I took that so it wouldn't get lost. See?
А, их я убрал, чтобы не потерялись. Вот, видите?
Stupid old geezer...
Чёртов старикашка...
Huh?
Что?
This sheet music is for Moonlight!
Это же ноты «Лунной» сонаты.
What?!
Что?!
Moonlight?!
«Лунной» сонаты?
What're you doing? You suck!
Да ты ужасно играешь.
No, this fourth bar is weird...
Нет же! Здесь странный четвёртый такт...
Fourth bar?
Четвёртый такт?
Maybe this sheet music is actually...
Возможно, в этих нотах...
...Kawashima-san's dying message...
предсмертная записка Кавасимы...
If so, then the killer might come back for it!
Значит, убийца может вернуться за ней.
Pardon me...
Извините...
When I asked for you at the hotel, they said you were all here...
В гостинице сказали, что вы здесь...
Dr. Narumi...
Наруми...
I brought some dinner.
Я принесла вам ужин.
Come to think of it...
Кстати об этом...
...we could use some food...
Еда будет весьма кстати.
So you're not originally from this island then, Dr. Narumi?
Так вы здесь не живёте, Наруми?
No. I return to Tokyo on the weekends.
Нет. Я возвращаюсь в Токио на выходных.
It's almost like I work as a part-time doctor here!
Я будто подрабатываю врачом!
I've always wanted to work on a small island like this,
Всегда хотелось работать на маленьком острове,
surrounded by nature...
цветущем и благоухающем...
I've been working here for 2 years now!
И я работаю здесь уже два года.
Dr. Narumi.
Наруми.
Did Mayor Kameyama really die of a heart attack two years ago?
Мэр Камэяма два года назад правда умер от сердечного приступа?
Yes. He had always had heart troubles...
Да. У него было слабое сердце...
But his face looked rather convulsive,
Но на лице было такое выражение,
almost as if he saw something horrifying...
будто он увидел что-то ужасное...
Did you notice anything strange at the time?
А ничего странного вы не заметили?
Hmm, now that you mention it...
Если задуматься...
What?
Что?
I think one of the windows was open.
Одно из окон было открыто.
A window?
Окон?
I believe we chalked that up to someone forgetting to close it, but...
Мы тогда решили, что кто-то забыл его закрыть...
Which window was it?
И какое окно?
If I remember right...
Кажется...
...it was this window.
вот это.
Who's there?!
Кто там?!
Stop!
Стоять!
You're not getting away!
Не уйдёшь!
Damn it! We lost him!
Чёрт! Скрылся!
I was right! He did come back to get this sheet music!
Я был прав. Он вернулся за нотами.
Okay! We're going to stay up all night and keep watch over this place!
Так! Останемся на ночь и будем сторожить!
Agreed?!
Согласны?
Agreed!
Да!
Hey. Mori-kun.
Эй, Мори.
Mori-kun!
Мори!
It's afternoon.
Уже день.
Inspector Megure-dono... What are you doing here?
Инспектор Мэгурэ... а вы здесь откуда?
This island's technically part of Tokyo.
Этот остров относится к Токио.
Oh, yeah. Where did I put it?
А, точно. Куда я их дел?
If you're looking for the sheet music, Conan-kun gave it to me.
Если ищешь ноты — Конан их уже отдал.
He also gave me the gist of the situation here.
Он также ввёл меня в курс дела.
All three of them were still awake by the time I arrived.
К моему приезду они ещё не спали.
You and that old man were the only ones asleep.
Спал только ты и тот старик.
They're interrogating people over at the town hall.
Горожан сейчас опрашивают.
Come give them a hand.
Помоги моим ребятам.
Sure...
Ладно...
We really shouldn't have slept there...
Не стоило нам там спать...
Dad! Well? Did you figure out who did it?
Ну что, пап? Понял, кто убийца?
Yeah, right. There were 38 people at the memorial.
Да если бы. На поминках было тридцать восемь человек.
It won't be that easy.
Не так-то это просто.
Sorry, but when will it be my turn?
Простите, а когда мой черёд?
You seem exhausted, so you're scheduled to be last.
Вы и так устали, так что опрошу вас напоследок.
In that case, I think I'll go wash my face in the ladies' room.
В таком случае пойду умоюсь.
How many more interviewees are there?
И много там ещё народу?
Including Dr. Narumi, there's six--
Если считать Наруми, шестеро...
the mayor's daughter, Reiko Kuroiwa,
дочь мэра, Рэйко Куроива,
her fiancé, Shuichi Murasawa,
её жених, Сюити Мурасава,
mayoral candidate, Masato Shimizu,
кандидат в мэры, Масато Симидзу,
the mayor's secretary, Kazuaki Hirata,
секретарь мэра, Кадзуаки Хирата
and Ken Nishimoto, who we're interviewing right now,
и Кэн Нисимото, которого мы опрашиваем,
but he's really wasting our time.
но из него ничего не выбьешь.
He won't say a word, no matter what we ask him.
Он молчит, что ни спроси.
My instincts say he did it!
Нутром чую, что это он!
Idiot! There's no curse on the piano!
Глупцы! Это проклятие рояля!
As long as that thing's around, these murders will keep happening!
Пока оно здесь, убийства будут продолжаться!
But, Mayor...
Но, мэр...
Dispose of it immediately! You hear me, Hirata?!
Немедленно избавьтесь! Понял, Хирата?!
Y-Yes, sir!
Д-да!
Give me a break!
Хватит с меня такого.
I've had enough of this!
Пора с этим завязывать!
I have no motive for killing Kawashima-san!
У меня нет мотива на убийство Кавасимы!
Ugh!
Чёрт!
Wow, listen to Reiko-san go.
Как Рэйко разозлилась.
She's been shouting for 10 minutes straight.
Уже десять минут кричит.
That's strange.
Странно.
They're through questioning him, so why isn't Nishimoto-san leaving?
Нисимото уже опросили, так почему он не уходит?
Huh?
Что?
I need to go to the bathroom.
Мне нужно в туалет.
Huh? Did Nishimoto-san come in here just now?
Что? Нисимото разве не заходил?
No.
Нет.
Crap! He took the stairs!
Чёрт! По лестнице пошёл!
This music...
Эта музыка...
It's the second movement of Moonlight...
Вторая часть «Лунной» сонаты...
Where's it coming from?!
Откуда она доносится?
The broadcast room!
Трансляционная!
Nishimoto-san!
Нисимото!
Too late!
Опоздали.
No, don't go inside!
Не заходите внутрь!
Get the examiners and autopsy team here at once!
Вызовите экспертов для аутопсии.
Inspector.
Инспектор.
The autopsy team left for Tokyo this evening to work on Kawashima-san.
Коронеры уехали в Токио из-за Кавасимы.
What?!
Что?!
Damn it! Now, of all times!
Чёрт! Как не вовремя.
Um...
Ну...
I can do it...
Я могу помочь...
Dr. Narumi...
Наруми...
But now this narrows down the suspects to a handful of people!
Но это значительно сузило круг подозреваемых.
So the killer is still--
Так убийца всё ещё...
All the exits to this building are guarded by police.
Полицейские охраняют все выходы.
Damn it!
Чёрт!
Who is it? Who's the killer?!
Кто же?! Кто из них убийца?!
It appears only a few minutes have passed since the victim's death.
Со смерти прошло всего несколько минут.
Yes, the first 5 minutes and 30 seconds of this tape seem to be blank.
Да, первые пять с половиной минут плёнки пустые.
Inspector Megure!
Инспектор Мэгурэ!
There was something strange beneath the body!
Мы нашли что-то у тела!
What?!
Что?
Sheet music?
Ноты?
Is this another dying message from the victim?
Очередная предсмертная записка?
No.
Нет.
If he had the time and strength to write all this with his own blood,
Если бы у него были силы на такую записку кровью,
he would've called for help instead.
он позвал бы на помощь.
The killer probably left each of these behind to--
Скорее всего, убийца намеренно оставил...
You stay out of this!
А ты не лезь!
Oh no! That's important evidence!
Вот чёрт! Это же важная улика!
It's okay!
О, не смазалось.
You're in the way! Get out of here!
Ты мешаешь! Уходи отсюда.
Seeing as Beethoven's Moonlight Sonata was played after each murder,
Учитывая, что после каждого убийства играла «Лунная»
it would seem the same person killed Kawashima-san and Kuroiwa-san.
соната Бетховена, Кавасиму и Куроиву, возможно, убил один человек.
And judging from the amount of blank tape,
А если брать во внимание пустую плёнку,
Kuroiwa-san must have been killed
Куроиву, вероятно, убили
around 6:30, only minutes before he was found.
около половины седьмого, за пару минут до обнаружения.
In other words, the killer must have been one of you,
Другими словами, убийца — один из вас,
since you were the only ones in the community center at the time!
ведь только вы были в дворце культуры.
Excluding Mori-kun and the others,
Кэн Нисимото
that leaves us with Ken Nishimoto-san, who was the first to find him,
остаются нашедший его Кэн Нисимото,
Dr. Narumi Asai, who was kind enough to inspect the body for us just now,
Наруми Асай
Kazuaki Hirata-san, secretary to the late Mayor Kuroiwa,
Кадзуаки Хирата
Mayor Kuroiwa's daughter, Reiko Kuroiwa-san
дочь мэра Куроивы, Рэйко Куроива
and her fiancé, Shuichi Murasawa-san.
и её жених, Сюити Мурасава.
And then Masato Shimizu-san, candidate in the mayoral election.
Масато Симидзу
Hold on! Why am I a suspect?!
Подождите! Почему я в списке подозреваемых?!
You've been questioning me since 6:20!
Вы допрашивали меня с шести двадцати!
You're right, you couldn't have done it...
И то верно, вы не смогли бы убить...
Then you can exclude Dr. Narumi too!
Тогда и Наруми можно исключить.
She's been with us since 6:00.
Она была с нами с шести часов.
Right, Conan-kun?
Верно, Конан?
Yeah!
Да.
So that leaves the four men as the only suspects...
Остаются четверо подозреваемых...
Excuse me, but I've been on this floor since 6:00 or so...
Извините, но я был на этом этаже с шести часов...
Do you have anyone to substantiate this?
Кто-то может это подтвердить?
You can all vouch for me, right?
Вы ведь заступитесь за меня?
Sorry, but I went to the restroom around 6:30.
Прости, но я полседьмого ушёл в туалет.
Tell me, Nishimoto-san...
Скажите, Нисимото...
You were the first person to find Kuroiwa-san...
Вы первым нашли Куроиву...
What exactly were you doing there?
Почему вы вообще были здесь?
Kuroiwa said he wanted to see me.
Куроива хотел со мной встретиться.
Are you sure you didn't ask to see him so you could kill him?!
А не вы вызвали его для убийства?!
No!
Нет!
It was Shimizu!
Это Симидзу!
With Kawashima and my father taken out of the election,
Раз Кавасима и мой отец выбыли из борьбы,
he'd automatically wind up in the mayor's seat!
он автоматически станет мэром!
Oh? What are you looking at, Conan-kun?
О? Что ты изучаешь, Конан?
Don't be stupid!
Не несите чушь!
The sheet music the killer left at the murder scene.
Ноты, которые были на месте преступления.
My guess is that it's a coded message from the murderer.
Предполагаю, это особый шифр от убийцы.
I wonder if there's anything special about these sharps and flats...
Имеют ли диезы и бемоли особое значение...
Those are the black keys on the keyboard. You know?
Это же чёрные клавиши на клавиатуре.
Keyboard?
Клавиатуре?..
Arrest this homicidal maniac before he kills anyone else--
Арестуйте этого маньяка-убийцу, пока он...
Better watch out. You're next.
Я понял. Следующий — вы. Готовьтесь.
Conan-kun?
Конан?
This code's easy if you know how to read it.
Если понять суть, то шифр довольно прост.
It's based on the notes that correspond with specific piano keys
Он основан на нотах, совпадающих с клавишами фортепиано,
if you arrange the letters of the alphabet across a piano keyboard.
если их обозначить в алфавитном порядке.
Using this, the music found where Kawashima-san was killed says,
Таким образом, на месте убийства Кавасимы было написано:
"Better watch out. You're next."
«Следующий — вы. Готовьтесь».
See?
Видите?
You're amazing, Conan-kun!
Ты такой молодец, Конан!
What does the other sheet music say?!
А что значит второе послание?
Let's see...
Так...
"Extinguished is the anger of the hellfire."
«Потушен гнев адского пламени».
The anger of the hellfire?! Could it be...
Гнев адского пламени?! Неужели...
...that pianist who killed himself in a fire 12 years ago?!
речь о пианисте, сгоревшем двенадцать лет назад?!
It's him! Keiji Aso's alive!
Это он! Кэйдзи Асо жив!
No he isn't.
Вовсе нет.
The bones found in the ashes matched his dental records--
Кости, найденные на пепелище, совпали с зубной картой...
he's most certainly dead.
он определённо мёртв.
Everything was completely scorched.
Абсолютно всё сгорело.
All that was left was some sheet music in a fireproof safe.
Остались только ноты в огнеупорном сейфе.
Sheet music?!
Ноты?!
Where? Where is this sheet music?!
Где? Где эти ноты?
In the community center storeroom.
В подсобке дворца культуры.
But the key to the storeroom's back at the station--
Но ключ от неё был в участке...
Then go get it!
Так иди и возьми его!
Alright!
Бегу!
Wait, Officer! I'm coming too!
Погодите! Я с вами.
Conan-kun!
Конан!
Say, did Aso-san really set his own house on fire?
Так Асо и правда поджёг свой дом?
Yes, there were four eyewitnesses.
Да. Было четыре свидетеля.
Our previous mayor, Kameyama-san,
Прошлый мэр, Камэяма,
Mayor Kuroiwa, Nishimoto-san, and Kawashima-san.
мэр Куроива, Нисимото и Кавасима.
Were those four connected in any way?
Эти четверо как-то связаны?
They were all classmates, including Aso-san.
Они были одноклассниками Асо.
Then what about that Murasawa guy?
А что насчёт этого Мурасавы?
He showed up on the island 3 years ago.
А... Он приехал на остров года три назад.
He and the mayor's daughter Reiko-san were engaged not too long ago.
Недавно они с дочерью мэра Рэйко обвенчались.
The mayor opposed it, though.
Хотя мэр был против.
What about Hirata, the mayor's secretary?
А Хирата, секретарь мэра?
He's suspicious if you ask me.
По мне так он скользкий тип.
I'm not quite sure what the deal was,
Уж не знаю, что он замышляет,
but he was always sneaking around with Kawashima-san
но он постоянно крутился у Кавасимы
at the community center.
во дворце культуры.
What about Shimizu?
А Симидзу?
He has a strong sense of justice and he's very popular with the fishermen!
Он преисполнен чувством справедливости и популярен у рыбаков!
Are you out of questions, Akechi-kun?
У тебя закончились вопросы, Акэти?
Eh?
А?
Huh? That's odd!
Что? Как странно.
I could swear it was around here somewhere...
Кажется, он был где-то здесь...
Come on. You've been looking for over an hour now.
Да ладно. Ты уже час ищешь.
Here we go! Here's the key!
Вот он! Нужный ключик!
Officer!
Полицейский!
Ran...?
Ран?
You took too long!
Как же вы долго.
Everyone grew tired of waiting so they went home!
Все устали и ушли домой!
All the suspects left?!
Подозреваемые разошлись?!
Yeah.
Ну да.
The killer's last message said that the hellfire's anger was extinguished,
В послании значилось, что гнев адского пламени потух,
so they figured there would be no more murders.
так что они решили, что убийств не будет.
Idiots!
Что за чушь!
Only the 1st and 2nd movements of Moonlight have been played
Пока что на местах преступлений были
at each of the murder scenes so far!
сыграны первая и вторая часть «Лунной» сонаты!
Moonlight has one movement left!
У «Лунной» сонаты есть и третья часть!
I'm going to check out the community center!
Я схожу во дворец культуры!
Wait! Conan-kun!
Погоди, Конан!
Talk about curious, Conan-kun...
Какой же ты любопытный, Конан...
Hurry!
Скорее!
Just hold on, will you?
Погоди немного.
Did you just hear a strange sound come from the piano room?
Слышали странный шум из комнаты с роялем?
No...
Нет...
Conan-kun!
Конан!
Stop!
Стоять!
Murasawa-san!
Мурасава!
Ran!
Ран!
The storeroom!
Подсобка!..
Officer! Go call Inspector Megure!
Вызовите инспектора Мэгурэ!
I'm on it!
Понял!
Was the 3rd movement played?
Играла третья часть?
There's 30 minutes per side on this tape,
На каждой стороне по полчаса,
which means Nishimoto-san died within the last 30 minutes!
так что Нисимото умер в течение этого времени!
Look, Conan-kun!
Смотри, Конан.
There's some more sheet music at Nishimoto-san's feet!
У него под ногами снова ноты!
What does it say this time?
Что написано на этот раз?
"Will."
«Воля».
It's his will?!
Воля?!
Then does that mean...
То есть...
It was a suicide?
Самоубийство?
According to the will,
Согласно записке,
he regretted killing Mr. Kawashima and Mr. Kuroiwa...
он сожалел об убийстве Кавасимы и Куроивы...
Nishimoto killed the two of them?!
Нисимото убил обоих?!
He apparently didn't want an old mistake they made to be made known.
Похоже, он не хотел раскрытия их былых ошибок.
"They" refers to Mr. Kameyama, who died 2 years ago,
Речь идёт об умершем два года назад Камэяме,
Mr. Kawashima and Mr. Kuroiwa, who were just killed,
только убитых Кавасиме и Куроиве,
Mr. Nishimoto, who hanged himself,
повесившемся Нисимото
and Mr. Aso, who killed himself 12 years ago.
и Асо, умершем двенадцать лет назад.
The pianist too?
И о пианисте?
My guess is that they did something, using this code.
Похоже, они сделали что-то с этим шифром.
I see. Nishimoto-san was afraid their old secret would get out
Вот как. Нисимото боялся, что их тайна будет раскрыта,
so he broke into the storeroom to destroy the sheet music.
и вломился в подсобку, чтобы уничтожить ноты.
But unable to find the music and driven into a psychological corner,
Но он не смог найти их и совершил самоубийство
he committed suicide.
из-за психологического давления.
I don't think it was a suicide.
Думаю, это не самоубийство.
It's impossible to hang yourself without something to support you, right?
Без опоры для ног невозможно повеситься.
Are you sure you didn't put it away?
Уверен, что не убрал её?
Of course not.
Разумеется.
And I doubt there's anyone who would go and write their own will in code.
И вряд ли кто-то стал бы писать предсмертную волю в шифре.
Are you saying the murderer is somewhere else?
То есть убийца — кто-то другой?
I saw some suspicious people.
Я видел кое-кого подозрительного.
What?!
Что?!
Two people in the piano room.
Двоих в комнате с роялем.
One broke a window and escaped.
Один разбил окно и сбежал.
The other was that Murasawa guy.
А другим был Мурасава.
Someone beat him up.
Кто-то его избил.
Dr. Narumi's treating him in the piano room right now.
Сейчас Наруми обрабатывает его раны.
Ow!
Ай!
Why didn't you say that sooner?!
Раньше бы сказал!
Dad!
Папа!
You still haven't found Mr. Aso's sheet music?!
До сих пор не нашли ноты Асо?
It was 12 years ago. There's no way for me to remember where we put it.
Я не помню, где они, это же было очень давно.
Is he still unconscious?
До сих пор без сознания?
Yes. I think he may have suffered a concussion.
Да. Возможно, у него сотрясение.
Say, Kuroiwa-san.
Скажите мне, Куроива...
What was Murasawa-san doing here this late anyway?
Почему Мурасава был здесь в такой час?
How should I know?!
А мне-то откуда знать?!
This is a...
Это же...
Keep your hands off Shuichi's stuff!
Не трогай вещи Сюити!
What is that?
Что это?
Don't ask me! But it was important to Shuichi!
Я не знаю, но это важная для Сюити вещь!
That's a tuning hammer, used to tune pianos.
Это же молоточек для настройки фортепиано.
So he was the one who...
Так это он...
Okay! Bring all the suspects to the town hall at once!
Так! Приведите сюда всех подозреваемых.
Yes, sir!
Да!
What are you doing, Conan-kun?
Что ты делаешь, Конан?
Let's go to the town hall.
Пойдём в мэрию.
The suspicious person who ran out of this room
Тот, кто выбежал отсюда,
was looking for something under the piano.
что-то искал под роялем.
Here we are!
Вот оно!
Wow, a hidden panel! Cool!
Да ладно, здесь двойное дно!
Drugs!
Наркотики!
Tsukikage Island Town Hall
Мэрия острова Цукикагэ
Judging from the methods employed in all three murders,
Судя по тому, как были убиты жертвы,
they are all clearly the work of the same person!
всё это провернул один человек!
Dr. Narumi and Reiko Kuroiwa-san have confirmed alibis
У Наруми и Рэйко Куроивы есть алиби,
and are no longer suspects.
они вне подозрений.
But there are no alibis for the secretary Hirata-san,
Но при этом нет алиби у секретаря Хираты,
the mayoral candidate Shimizu-san,
кандидата в мэры Симидзу
nor for Murasawa-san, who is currently resting at the clinic...
и Мурасавы, который сейчас в больнице...
The killer is one of these three!
Убийца — один из вас троих!
Dr. Narumi. Is Murasawa-san still unconscious?
Доктор Наруми. Мурасава ещё без сознания?
Yes. Reiko-san is looking after him, but he has yet to regain consciousness.
Да. Рэйко присматривает за ним, но он ещё не очнулся.
There's something nagging at me, but what could it be?!
Что-то мне не даёт покоя. Что же?
Ever since I saw the code of blood left at the scene of the crime...
С того момента, как увидел кровавый шифр на месте преступления...
Inspector.
Инспектор.
The photos taken from where Mr. Kuroiwa was murdered are ready!
Готовы фотографии с места убийства Куроивы!
Good. Place them on that desk.
Отлично. Разложите на столе.
Yes, sir!
Да.
What's that light by Kuroiwa-san's neck?
Что это у шеи Куроивы?
It's off in the picture where he's been moved.
На следующей фотографии её нет.
Um, may I buy some juice? I'm thirsty...
А можно сходить купить сока? Жажда замучила...
I suppose that'd be alright.
Ну, пусть сходит.
He's injured?
Он поранился?
Say, Mister.
Послушайте.
There's some white powder on your sleeves.
У вас на рукавах белый порошок.
What?!
Что?!
Money from all over the world!
Сколько иностранных монет!
I'm fond of foreign countries.
Я люблю зарубежье.
What's wrong, Officer?
Что такое, полицейский?
I finally found the sheet music Aso-san left behind!
Я наконец нашёл ноты, которые оставил Асо!
Let me see that!
Ну-ка покажите.
"To my son, Seiji."
«Моему сыну Сэйдзи».
Son?
Сыну?
He fell seriously ill when he was little and had to be hospitalized...
Он был серьёзно болен в детстве и попал в больницу...
I believe Seiji was his name...
Кажется, его звали Сэйдзи...
Seiji?!
Сэйдзи?
It couldn't be!
Не может быть!
Hey, wait! Where do you think you're going?!
Постой-ка. Куда ты собрался?
Ah, now I see!
Теперь-то всё ясно!
The reason the killer dragged Kawashima-san into the piano room
Я понял, почему убийца после утопления
after drowning him!
затащил Кавасиму к роялю.
The meaning of the music played at the murder scenes!
Значение музыки на местах преступления!
And the mystery behind the code written in blood!
Тайна, скрытая за кровавым шифром!
There's no doubt about it! That's the one who did it!
Я уверен в том, кто был убийцей!
Mr. Mori received a letter from a dead man
Дядя Мори получил письмо от мертвеца
and then headed to Tsukikage Island.
и направился на остров Цукикагэ.
The letter's author was Keiji Aso, a pianist who murdered his family,
Автором был пианист Кэйдзи Асо, который убил свою семью,
lit his house on fire, and died while playing the Moonlight piano sonata.
поджёг свой дом и умер, исполняя «Лунную» сонату.
The 1st murder happened on the night of the memorial for Mr. Kameyama,
Первое убийство произошло в ночь поминок Камэямы,
the previous mayor.
бывшего мэра города.
Hideo Kawashima was found dead in the piano room,
Хидэо Кавасиму нашли в комнате с роялем,
while the first movement of Moonlight played.
когда играла первая часть «Лунной» сонаты.
The second murder took place as the second movement played.
Второе убийство было совершено под вторую часть сонаты.
The victim was the current mayor, Tatsuji Kuroiwa.
Жертвой стал действующий мэр, Тацудзи Куроива.
The number of suspects was narrowed down to six people.
Подозреваемых осталось шестеро.
The third murder was that of Ken Nishimoto.
Третьим был убит Кэн Нисимото.
He was killed in a manner that made it look like suicide.
Внешне всё выглядело как самоубийство.
"To my son, Seiji."
«Моему сыну Сэйдзи».
Ah, now I see!
Теперь-то всё ясно!
The reason the killer dragged Kawashima-san into the piano room
Я понял, почему убийца после утопления
after drowning him!
затащил Кавасиму к роялю.
The meaning of the music played at the murder scenes!
Значение музыки на местах преступления!
And the mystery behind the code written in blood!
Тайна, скрытая за кровавым шифром!
There's no doubt about it! That's the one who did it!
Я уверен в том, кто был убийцей!
What's the big idea, rushing here to the broadcast room like that?!
И зачем так бежать в трансляционную?
Is there something here?!
Здесь что-то есть?
No, not really.
Нет, не особо.
I've got no choice! I'll have to use the old man's voice for this!
Выбора нет! Придётся использовать голос Мори!
One shot of this Anesthetic Watch Gun and...
Использую часы-транквилизатор...
Hirata-san and Shimizu-san will have to come to the mainland with us
Хирата и Симидзу завтра утром отправятся
tomorrow morning.
с нами в Токио.
You can't be serious!
Как же так!
The first incident, in which Mr. Kawashima was drowned
В первом инциденте Кавасиму утопили
and dragged into the community center's piano room last night...
и затащили в комнату с роялем прошлой ночью...
The second incident, in which Mr. Kuroiwa was murdered
Во втором инциденте Куроива был убит
in the broadcast room this very night...
в трансляционной этой ночью...
The third incident, which also took place this very night,
В третьем инциденте, также этой ночью,
in which Mr. Nishimoto was killed in the storeroom
Нисимото был убит в подсобке,
in such a way to make it look like a suicide...
и всё выглядело как самоубийство...
The only ones without alibis for these three incidents are you two
Единственные, у кого нет алиби на все случаи, это вы
and Murasawa-san, who is resting at the clinic.
и Мурасава, который сейчас в больнице.
I'm sorry to do this, but we'll have to watch you tonight.
Очень жаль, но придётся за вами понаблюдать.
I've figured it out, Inspector!
Я со всем разобрался, инспектор!
Almost everything about the murders on this island, that is.
Почти со всем касательно этих убийств.
Dad! You're in the broadcast room?
Папа! Ты в трансляционной?
First, the person who beat Murasawa-san unconscious in the piano room.
Для начала тот, кто вырубил Мурасаву в комнате с роялем.
That would be you, Hirata-san!
Это были вы, Хирата!
What?!
Что?
Hirata-san suffered the injury on his left hand
От разбивания окна для побега
when he broke the window and escaped.
у Хираты рана на левой руке.
You were also the suspicious person we saw last night.
Вы же были подозрительным человеком вчера.
But what was he doing?
Но чем он был занят?
He was making deals with Mr. Kawashima in that room.
Он заключал сделки с Кавасимой в той самой комнате.
Drug deals.
Наркотики.
Drugs?!
Наркотики?!
Hirata-san used a hidden panel in the piano
Хирата использовал двойное дно в рояле
to trade drugs he bought overseas for large sums of money.
для продажи зарубежных наркотиков за немалые деньги.
Aha! So that's why they were at the community center every single night!
Так вот почему они каждую ночь ходили во дворец культуры!
The reason Hirata-san always claimed the piano was cursed
Хирата утверждал, что рояль проклят,
was to keep people from getting in the way.
чтобы отвести от него людей.
He probably assaulted Murasawa-san and escaped
Он напал на Мурасаву и сбежал,
because Murasawa-san saw him taking back the drugs he had left there!
потому что его застали за забором наркотиков!
Does that mean you killed Mr. Kawashima
Так вы убили Кавасиму,
because you were having a dispute with him about the deals?!
так как не сошлись на условиях сделки?
No!
Нет!
Hirata-san has nothing to do with the three murders.
Хирата не имеет отношения к этим убийствам.
If he was the murderer, he wouldn't have killed anyone in the piano room.
Будь он убийцей, все уже были бы мертвы.
That was the room where he left the drugs, after all.
Он ведь там оставлял наркотики.
Next is Murasawa-san.
Следующий Мурасава.
He's the killer?!
Так это был он?
He's not the killer either.
Он никого не убивал.
The reason the killer wrote a will to make it look a suicide
Убийца выставил всё как самоубийство,
but didn't place an object to stand on in the room
но не подставил опору,
was because the murderer bolted when Ran and the others showed up.
потому что пришли Ран с Конаном.
It would have been impossible to enter the piano room afterward.
Затем он уже не мог войти в комнату.
You're right!
Точно ведь!
So far, our image of the killer has been that of a man,
Мы считали, что убийца — мужчина,
because all three murders required someone with strength.
потому что для таких убийств требовалась сила.
And someone without an alibi.
И кто-то без алиби.
The only suspect left is Shimizu-san...
Остался только Симидзу...
Next, we need to look at the second murder.
Нужно обратить внимание на второе убийство.
We assumed Kuroiwa-san was killed only minutes before he was found.
Мы предположили, что Куроиву убили за пару минут до нас.
But if you'll remember...
Но если задуматься...
...the blood code didn't come off when Conan fell on it.
кровавый шифр не смазался, когда на него упал Конан.
At room temperature, it takes 15 to 30 minutes for human blood to dry.
При комнатной температуре кровь высыхает за 15-30 минут.
But that blood was dry,
Но она уже высохла,
even though he was supposedly killed only minutes before.
хотя Куроиву должны были убить недавно.
That's right. It was a trick the killer did to alter the estimated time of death.
Верно. Это трюк убийцы с ложным временем смерти.
What?!
Что?!
But only the first 5 and a half minutes of the tape were blank!
Но на плёнке нет звука только в первые пять с половиной минут!
Automatic tape reverse.
Автоматическая перемотка.
The killer played the 2nd side of the tape, which had no music on it
Убийца включил пустую сторону кассеты.
and gained 30 extra minutes by using tape reverse.
Так он получил лишние полчаса для убийства.
Please have a look at the photographs.
Взгляните на фотографии.
There's a button lit near Kuroiwa-san's neck.
У шеи Куроивы горит кнопка.
And the light is off just after his body is moved.
А когда тело сдвинули, свет пропал.
That's proof that the killer turned it off when you weren't looking.
Это доказывает, что убийца выключил кассету, пока вы отвернулись.
But if I remember correctly, the one who approached the body was--
Но около тела в тот момент был только...
That's right.
Верно.
The person who got near the body, aside from the police...
Тот, кто подошёл к телу помимо полиции...
The person who faked the estimated time of death...
И тот, кто сказал ложное время смерти...
...was the one who inspected the body--you, Dr. Narumi!
это человек, обследовавший тело... вы, доктор Наруми!
That's not true, is it, Dr. Narumi?!
Это ведь неправда, Наруми?
You drowned Kawashima-san and dragged him into the piano room
Вы утопили Кавасиму и затащили в комнату с роялем,
in order to send the coroners back to the mainland,
чтобы отправить коронеров в Токио,
since they wouldn't be able to examine an unnatural death here.
потому что здесь неестественную смерть не изучить.
And the reason you put blank space at the start of each tape
И пустое место на каждой стороне кассеты
was so that you could throw us off by faking the time of the 2nd murder.
было для того, чтобы мы не поняли время второго убийства.
Doing this, you altered Kuroiwa-san's time of death,
Таким образом вы изменили время смерти Куроивы,
thereby creating an alibi for yourself.
создав себе алиби.
But Mori-kun! You just said the killer was a man!
Но, Мори! Ты же сказал, что убийца — мужчина!
The motive for the murders extends 12 years back.
Мотив для убийств появился двенадцать лет назад.
Come again?
Эй!
Back to the incident in which pianist Keiji Aso and his family were killed.
Тогда были убиты пианист Кэйдзи Асо и его семья.
Killed?!
Убиты?!
Kawashima-san, Nishimoto-san, Kuroiwa-san,
Кавасима, Нисимото, Куроива
and the previous mayor, Kameyama-san...
и прошлый мэр, Камэяма...
They used Aso-san's international performances
использовали международные гастроли
as opportunities to buy and sell drugs.
Асо для покупки и продажи наркотиков.
But then Aso-san said he refused to help them any longer.
Но затем Асо отказался им помогать.
Afraid their secret would get out,
Боясь, что их тайна будет раскрыта,
they shut him and his family inside his house and set it on fire.
они закрыли его в доме с семьёй и подожгли.
This is all written in the sheet music that survived that fire...
Всё написано в нотах, которые пережили тот пожар...
In the confession letter that Aso-san wrote for his child...
В признании, которое Асо написал своему сыну...
A son?!
Сыну?!
He had a son in a Tokyo hospital.
У него был сын в токийской больнице.
One named Seiji.
Сына звали Сэйдзи.
Seiji? It couldn't be...
Сэйдзи? Неужели...
Dr. Narumi's real name is Seiji.
На самом деле Наруми зовут Сэйдзи.
She was Keiji Aso's son, Seiji Aso!
Она и была сыном Кэйдзи Асо, Сэйдзи!
Asai is probably his foster family's last name.
Скорее всего, Асаи — фамилия приёмной семьи.
So it was all to avenge his father...
Так всё ради мести за отца...
Inspector! The killer's gone!
Инспектор! Убийца сбежал!
Find him!
Найдите его!
I know where he is!
Я знаю, где он.
The place where Aso Keiji's donated piano is kept--the community center!
Там, где хранился рояль от Кэйдзи Асо... во дворце культуры!
It's over, Father.
Всё кончено, отец.
It's not over yet!
Ещё ничего не кончено!
Here, look at this!
Вот, взгляните.
It's written in this sheet music your dad left for you!
Это написано в нотах, оставленных вам.
He says he wants you to live an honest life!
Отец хотел, чтобы вы жили как следует.
I wish I had known that sooner.
Я хотел это услышать.
How did you find out about your father if you haven't read this?!
А как вы узнали об отце, если не читали послание?
I always had my suspicions about my foster father.
Я всегда подозревал приёмного отца.
After graduating from medical school,
После медицинского
I came to this island as a woman doctor.
я приехал сюда в качестве женщины-врача.
It doesn't say on my license how to pronounce my name, after all.
На лицензии же не написано, как читается имя.
But I was sweating bullets when they started questioning people.
Но во время допроса я порядком занервничал.
They would've found out I was really a man.
Они могли раскрыть мой пол.
I see. So that's why you stayed with us that night--
Вот как. Поэтому вы остались с нами...
so you could have them question you last.
чтобы вас опрашивали последним.
When I told Kameyama, the previous mayor, that I was Aso's son,
Когда я сказал прошлому мэру, что я сын Асо,
he suddenly grew fearful and told me everything.
он испугался и всё мне рассказал.
He finished it all off by falling lifeless from a heart attack.
А в конце упал замертво от приступа.
It was when I played my father's favorite piece, Moonlight,
Тогда я сыграл любимое произведение отца, «Лунную» сонату,
as a farewell song for him that I came up with the idea for these murders.
прощальную мелодию, давшую начало убийствам.
Seiji! Let's get out of here! We can still make it!
Сэйдзи! Нам нужно убираться!
It's too late for me.
Уже слишком поздно.
These hands are as bloodstained as theirs are.
Мои руки тоже запятнаны кровью.
Conan-kun!
Конан!
Dammit!
Чёрт!
No!
Нет!
Let go!
Отпусти!
What's that sound?
Что это за звук?
This is the code.
Это шифр.
He's playing it. Inside the fire.
Он играет даже в языках пламени.
Murasawa-san missed Keiji Aso, the pianist,
Мурасава скучал по пианисту Кэйдзи Асо
so he apparently tuned his piano on occasion...
и на всякий случай настраивал инструмент...
On the night he was assaulted, too.
Даже в ночь, когда на него напали.
Why did Dr. Narumi warn us about the murders?
Зачем Наруми предупреждала нас об убийствах?
My only guess is that it was actually a letter of challenge to Dad...
Возможно, это был вызов моему отцу...
I think she wanted to be stopped from killing...
Скорее она, хотела, чтоб кто-то её остановил...
Say, what did the code that Dr. Narumi played say?
А что значил код, который играла Наруми?
Oh, I already forgot.
Я уже давно забыл.
Thank you, Little Detective
Спасибо, маленький детектив
Just my imagination
Лишь в воображении
Playing with threads around my finger while drinking lukewarm tea
игриво нити накрутил уже на пальцы, чай остывший давно до сих пор попиваю!
Let's walk lightly to the bossa nova rhythm
В ритме босса-нова шагаем, трудности преодолеваем,
The puzzle pieces are in my hands
И частички пазла уже у нас в руках!
That's right...
Вот так-так-так-так...
I was in the same place last week but with different clothes
Я в другой одежде на прошлой неделе... уже приходил сюда!
Step by step, there's no reason to be anxious
Шаг за шагом, нет причины излишне спешить!
Case by case, I don't care if you laugh
Дело за делом, ничуть меня не заботит ваш смех!
Don't tell me the car Ayumi-chan got in
Неужели Аюми залезла в машину тех людей,
belonged to those kidnappers who're killing little girls!
которые похищают и убивают девочек!
Hold on, Ayumi-chan! We're coming to save you!
Держись, Аюми, мы уже в пути!
On the next Conan--
Далее в «Конане»:
Ayumi-chan's Abduction.
«Похищение Аюми»!
Next Conan's Hint:
Следующая зацепка Конана:
A School Festival.
Школьный фестиваль.
Next episode is a little different from usual.
В следующий раз странная схема действий.